All right, let's start with a little introduction
to modeling or to this course in terms of
content.
Obviously, it
is about models.
And first of all, we should approach the
question of what kind of models we are
going to
talk about.
What
are models?
I'm sure you have some kind of
colloquial idea of a model, i.e. model
cars or a
3D model in architecture.
Yes, those are
all models, colloquially.
And the question
is, of course:
Are we also
concerned with such models?
And what is
to be modeled here?
Why?
And a
little bit already:
What are the different types and characteristics
of models that will be relevant to
us here
in the course?
Instead of just the
colloquial notion of model.
So first, of course, we
can try to just define.
What is modeling or what
is a model for us?
And defining that is not so easy
because it can mean just about anything.
As you can see from
the colloquial examples I just mentioned.
So for us, we
could define it like this:
A model is a representation, not
the real thing, but only a representation
of
something.
And that is of a, quite
generally speaking, system of objects, relations and/or
processes.
All these terms, "object", "relation", "processes",
could of course refer in computer
science to software
products for example.
But of course one can also capture
other real-world relationships in the same way.
So it's about representing
something, representing a system.
And then it says here:
a model simplifies and abstracts.
So as a rule, of
course, you don't make a model.
A model is not the real thing, so
the model car is not the real car, but
a simplification/abstraction
of it.
So somehow this system, which is
the issue, is simplified and abstracted.
For example, by
considering only relevant properties.
Of course, the question of what is
relevant depends on the purpose of the
model.
What do I want
to do with it?
Do I have the model car just to be
able to look at it, at home in the living
room, when I can't be pining
after my car in the garage?
Or do I want to
do something with the model?
For example, as an engineer, I might want
to investigate properties of the system by first
examining the
model more closely.
Other properties may be relevant
and therefore need to be simplified.
And systems can be
all kinds of things.
If I want to say up here that
we represent a system, then I have to ask
myself, or you
could ask me:
How do
you define "system"?
Again, very generally
used at first.
Of course, one can already think of a computer
science system, of a software, of a hardware prototype
for
example.
But in general we can say (and
many examples in the lecture will not
only be from the computer science
context), in general a system could either
reflect a part of reality or
be a section of reality, or a
not yet
existing entity.
So something that is there, that one
wants to describe, gladly by a model.
Or something that one wants to build/create and
therefore wants to look at a model in
advance, or create,
look at, work with.
So that is an
alternative, so to speak.
Does the system already exist or
is it yet to be created?
And another distinction
that is also relevant:
The system could
be something representational.
In the case of the model car, that
is representational, both the model car itself and
the real car of
which that is a model.
Both would
be representational things.
Or
virtual.
So if I look again at the 3D
model of a skyscraper to be built, then
the skyscraper as a system would
of course be a representational system of
objects, consisting of all its floors, the beams,
all the building materials, for example, and the
parts of the
skyscraper formed from them.
The 3D model, which is created on the
computer beforehand, is of course something only virtual.
But a system itself
could also be virtual.
When we talk about a software
system, it itself is not representational.
So both models and systems
can be representational or virtual.
And an information technology system
can also be representational, of course.
So an augmented reality system
that you might want to build.
That would
be the system.
And before that, you make
a plan of it, a model.
That's a very general
first version of these terms.
All right, then
what is modeling?
That's actually the
question up here.
So modeling is very likely the
process that gives rise to a model.
And actually we
take the starting point:
We have a system or
we want to create a system.
In order to be able to better grasp,
understand, analyze it, we first want to have a
model.
Modeling would then be this process
that creates a model for the system.
And for that, of
course, we need to simplify/abstract.
Since the model represents the system in
a simplifying and abstracting way, certain steps of
simplification have
to be taken.
And these can be quite different
model building processes, which we will see
in different forms
in the lecture.
For example, this includes delimiting what
of reality you actually want to
capture in
the model.
So you first have to cut the system out
of the overall reality in order to be able to
say what is
to be modeled here.
So you have to separate the
model, even the system, from the rest.
Reduction, simply
omitting details.
So you may not need to represent
the entire system in its full glory.
The model is usually simplified, just
like the model car doesn't contain all
the details, maybe not even the
engine, that is in the real car.
Because if you're just using the model car
to look at it, it doesn't need to
have
the engine.
So you can reduce things, you can decompose,
you can imagine the system broken down into its
parts, or capture how it's
actually made up of subsystems.
And that can lead to the fact that one
can form a model about it better, that one just
carries out this decomposition of the system
into its parts mentally and then models the
parts.
Then the overall model is simply
the sum of these partial models.
Or summarize things,
abstract from details.
So different processes, mental processes,
partly also technical processes, play a
role
there.
And we will see them in
action with many examples in this lecture.
Why are
we doing this?
Yes, that's what I've just
been hinting at again and again.
Maybe we want to design a
system first or understand an existing system
better.
Maybe we want to visualize it
to document it, maybe for other
users.
Maybe we want to do simulations
that we can't do on the
real system, but for which we'd
rather work with a simpler model.
And a system could just be there,
or it could be yet to be created.
It could be a computer science system or
a very general system coming from the world
of
handling.
To be a little
bit more concrete or
to remind you that you have of
course already worked with models, have already seen
models, here are a few short
slides on typical models, classical examples
from the
natural sciences.
Of course, a lot of work is done
with models, because you can't always fully grasp the
real systems that
are involved, for example.
Or because you can think
about certain questions better with models.
So, what would be such
a classic model from physics?
There are several
atomic models, for example.
According to current knowledge, atoms
consist of protons, neutrons and electrons.
Strictly speaking, these parts consist of even
smaller subparticles, but one could now say that
we are not interested
in that, for example.
There we carry out a simplification, an
abstraction and simply want to understand how atoms
on this decomposition level,
consist of these parts.
That's about how these particles interact,
how they make up an atom.
And there's actually
not just one model.
There's a whole series of models that
have been gradually refined and improved throughout
the history
of physics.
So, the beginning is made by Thomson's atomic model,
where it was already recognized that there is positive
and
negative charge.
And the idea here was
a bit like a raisin cake.
There is this big positively charged atom
and in it are peppered negative charge carriers.
This was imagined because one had
observed the electrons in the context
of
electric current.
So one knew, there
must be these charges.
The electrons are mobile,
or so one imagined it.
They are small particles embedded in a
big atom, and the charge is plus
and minus
the same.
And that's why the
atom as such is neutral.
Then there were further physical experiments and
it turned out that it cannot be
that the positive charge is distributed so
large, so to speak, in such a large
object.
But actually the atomic nucleus, which
carries only the positive charge, is much
smaller.
Rutherford's experiments have worked this
out or let it come out.
And therefore
the conclusion came:
No, there is this small nucleus,
which unites all positive charge, and the
negative electrons move around
it in a certain perimeter.
That is, a certain distance
that they do not leave.
They are so trapped
there near the nucleus.
Then there
were further observations.
The Bohr atomic model, which is
mostly used in school physics today, has
established that the electrons are not
just randomly distributed around the atomic nucleus,
but that they move
on shells, on certain paths.
And that this is very important for
chemical processes, for example: to know on which
positions the individual
electrons are located.
And that's why the Bohr
atomic model makes these additional statements
about how the electrons are
distributed around the atomic nucleus.
And with the quantum theory, quantum
physics, it has turned out that this
is actually not so simple, because
of the dual wave/particle character, to imagine
these electrons simply
hanging at certain positions.
But actually one must work
with orbits, thus distribution probabilities, where
the
particles are.
Because of the final character, that
these particles behave also like waves.
So there, in the end, it's all
about residence probabilities instead of actual specific position.
And now we could say, this is the
best model, this seems to correspond to the most
modern
physics.
But in fact, even these simple
models are still relevant in physics.
In particular, in school physics, this model
is usually used in the first place.
Because it is sufficiently and exactly correctly
detailed for the things, which one examines
there.
So one has had here consciously perhaps first
of all very simple models because of the
initially lower knowledge potential
or lower level of knowledge.
But even today, one can still decide on
a level of detail that represents the relationships to
be
investigated well.
And we should see that with other
models as well, that it can make sense
to have different modeling levels for the
same system, depending on what one actually wants
to
investigate.
Another example that I can't really say
too much about, this comes from biology.
It's quite nice here in the presentation, but
I can't say that much about the content, because
I'm not as well educated biologically myself
as I am physically, I would think.
So here, obviously, an
acid exchange cycle is described.
And I actually don't want to
go into individual parts at all.
But what's interesting, why it's also in
here: because it has a certain characteristic
difference to
the example before.
Namely, this seems to
be about a process.
Here it
was actually about:
How are
atoms constructed?
So back here these probability distributions
appear, that also has something dynamic.
So, how do
these particles move?
Where are
they, when?
But especially these first three
models here, they are rather static.
It's about which subparticles
does an atom consist of?
How are
they arranged?
Where are
they located?
Maybe also: with which
charges are they located?
With which energy levels are
they located on different levels?
But in essence, simply
a state is described.
This is what the
specific atom looks like.
Here, in this model, it's
obviously about describing a process.
That's why we're going to call this
a dynamic model, obviously for acid exchange cycle/processes.
Products
are transformed.
There is also some information here
for in what composition, in what ratio
the individual components
interact with each other.
But in any case,
a transformation is described here.
We will call this
a dynamic model shortly.
And this model came
up very briefly just now.
It's interesting in that it's very
graphical, perhaps in a very popular
scientific
way.
I wouldn't zoom in on it
now and describe the individual parts here.
But this is also something that you
know as a model, perhaps from geography lessons,
when somehow climate and processes
of the atmosphere were described.
What is striking about this model, but
also certainly about the two examples before it,
is that a lot of visual and
graphical transport and information is used here.
Of course, this does not
always have to be the case.
When it
comes to:
What kinds of models
are we going to have?
Or what kinds of models
will appear in computer science?
There is a
first difference, namely:
Is modeling
visual or textual?
The examples just
now were very visual.
Of course, you can also model with
more textual means, then for example verbal
descriptions or mathematical formulas, which are
also in some kind of context.
These would be mathematical models that
you encounter in logic, in algebra.
Depending on which mathematics lecture you have
already heard or are listening to in
parallel, you will
also encounter models.
These are not primarily the kind of
models we're going to look at here.
Because we will not look at
formal logical models in this course, because
there are other courses for that
in your respective courses of study.
Of course, this does not mean that
a model is always exactly only visual or
only
textual.
So the atomic models, which were somehow
also visually represented on the slide before
last, are of course actually also backed up
with formulas in physics, with the mathematical descriptive
relationships
behind them.
And that is then
again rather mathematical text.
In this course we will
often work with graphical representations.
Not as free-graphic as here (a colorful
picture), but already in a very disciplined way
to represent
something graphically.
So more formal than
here just a painted picture.
But also not as formal
as formal logic operates to describe
connections.
That has partly didactic reasons that you
see something like that in the course.
Of course, a graphical
representation helps to better understand
models.
And that's why graphical models or at
least model languages with visual components are
often used
in practice.
So that would be a first distinction:
visual model vs. textual model, but of
course there are
also intermediate levels.
Another distinction that can be
made is between so-called qualitative
and
quantitative models.
Qualitative, quantitative, that you know as
terms of course, simply from the
language.
So, qualitative,
somehow the description:
What,
How, Why?
Quantitative:
Description of
quantities or numbers.
How much,
how often?
So, typical questions for consideration
of qualitative models would be:
What objects
are there?
In the atom, what
objects occur in it?
Which small
particles, protons, electrons?
What characteristics/relationships do they
have to each other?
What
happens?
Not:
In what order,
how often, when?
But:
What
happens qualitatively?
Why does
it happen?
The reasons
for certain processes.
Maybe also the order/causal connections,
but no statements about quantities
or numbers
or numerical values/measurements.
So questions about:
what, how, why.
And in contrast
to that, quantitative models.
There it
is just about:
How many
objects are there?
In which quantity ratio do
these different kinds of objects occur?
How long might a process take (if
it is a process that is being modeled)?
How likely is
a particular event?
I had talked about probability
distribution in the fourth atomic model.
That would clearly then be a
quantitative aspect that is being modeled there.
In the lecture, we will be dealing
with qualitative models for the most part.
But there will also be some places
where quantitative aspects come into play, but
less
so.
Certainly also because, of course, you usually have
to say what objects there are in the first
place before you can
talk about "how many".
So of course "quantitative" is often
a refinement or enrichment of qualitative
models by
additional information.
That is, of the models we've
had here, probably the first three are
more
qualitative.
Whereas, especially in the Bohr atomic model,
you also have a quantitative aspect, because
you have these different energy levels
on which the electrons can move.
These would also be described by
numbers, or distances perhaps, or energy quantities.
The orbital model
is clearly quantitative.
There one calculates with
probabilities, these are number statements.
In the model one has in the
first place also certainly a qualitative modeling.
By this sequence, which is described,
and the listings or compilation of
the different products, which occur (chemical
products, which are in the game).
But there's also at least some quantitative
parts here, because we're talking about ratios of
substances and quantities of
substances, through these numbers here.
And here you also have more of a
qualitative model, because there are no formulas or
numbers.
Another distinction that will
be relevant is the question:
How visible, then, are
the internals of a model?
This is often framed as
black box versus white box.
So do we have a black box in front of
us, so to speak, where we can only describe behavior
that is observable from the outside, but we
don't know what is happening inside this black
box?
Or do we have such a glass
box, or white box in English, where
we can also describe what, why,
how this externally observable behavior is generated
inside
the system?
So if we imagine a software system,
then blackbox would simply be the description/modeling:
What happens from the user's point
of view when certain buttons are
pressed in
the program?
One can
only say:
If this and that is pressed, then the
following window opens and there is a certain message
in
it.
Whitebox would be, if one has also the
program code or at least a description of the
internal expirations (that does not have to be
the concrete program code), or perhaps a pseudo code
description of the internal expirations
of the system, before itself.
And you can also analyze why
a certain behavior occurs, or perhaps
a certain expected
behavior does not occur.
So you
could imagine:
Blackbox would be a description for
customers and offers more freedom to the
implementer, because only the externally observable behavior
is important (and internally can happen what seems
appropriate to
the developer).
Whitebox view of a system, a whitebox modeling,
would be important for the technical team that
is building a
particular software, for example.
Of course, this also has to deal with
how this behavior should be generated inside in
the
first place.
There are
also intermediate levels.
There is
the term greybox.
That would be "not completely visible", not
all details, but then also not completely
hidden, what
happens inside.
For us, this will be most
interesting in dynamic modeling or dynamic
modeling
parts.
Now I have already spoken several times
about static and dynamic without saying before what
exactly is
meant by that.
Certainly also because static
and dynamic as colloquial terms
are hopefully
clear enough.
So:
A static model primarily describes the
structure or a particular state of the
system.
Structure could
be, for example:
How is this
system composed of subsystems?
That could be aspects of the
structure that you want to describe.
Or at a
certain point in time:
What is the
state of the system?
Where are the electrons
lined up around the nucleus?
This might be about describing a
generally always fixed state, or if
the system has potential to evolve,
then the static description of the state
at a
particular time.
In
contrast:
A dynamic model at least
also describes how the system evolves.
So it could be that one or
more possible processes of the system are
described, or even the whole system
behavior with all its possible processes.
Of course, this will usually be based on
the fact that one first has a static
description.
You first have to know which parts the system
consists of, in order to then be able to say
how these parts change their
relationship to each other, for example.
So a dynamic model will often
include or build on a static model.
Of course, I had
said earlier, for example, here:
The first three models
are more static in nature.
This one is more dynamic because it's
also about these movements of the subparticles.
Here I
had also said:
It also has dynamic parts
because of these conversion processes obviously.
And also here, if you zoom in a
little bit, you would find some dynamic aspects.
And then we have another important distinction, which
is the degree of formality of the models.
So how accurate
are these models?
And there you can just go
from one extreme to the other.
You can have completely formal models, which
are mainly the models that you find in
mathematical lectures
or in logic.
So they are completely
exact in their statements.
Capture the relationships at stake completely
exactly (which may not always be
possible
in reality).
So formal models, if they exist, are
of course very nice, because they make very
precise
statements.
But reality is sometimes not to
be grasped in such a way.
That's why at the other extreme of
the spectrum, there are non-formal models that just
describe something
maybe verbally.
So if I ask you what a car
looks like, you can just make certain statements about
it that just
describe it colloquially.
That would
be very non-formal.
I can't derive any statements from that,
maybe how well this car will perform in
a
crash test.
I would need
something more formal there.
And then in the middle,
there are the so-called semi-formal models.
"Semi" for
"half" or "almost."
So these are models
that are partially exact.
They use certain notation, for example, in
order to be able to express parts
precisely, but they also
do not specify everything completely.
So they don't have the claim, like
an exact mathematical model, to capture everything on
the desired
modeling level.
And we will see formal models in
the lecture, especially in the Petri net part
(which is a typical quite
formal model, a formal modeling notation).
But a lot of the lecture will
be more in the area of semi-formal models.
So UML (this modeling language from
software engineering that I've already mentioned
at least in the literature part),
that's a classic example of semi-formal modeling.
And of course, the decision on which
of these three levels you move depends, on
the one hand, on
the skills and the possibilities.
So some things you just
can't describe with arbitrary precision.
And often, of
course, it's also about:
What is the
purpose of the model?
So, why
do you model?
This also determines how precise and
elaborate the description has to be.
If something is to be verified formally,
then the model should also be very formal.
If the main purpose is to
simply communicate about the system you are
dealing with, then a very
non-formal description may be sufficient.